Charles Flanders Papers
Charles Flanders Papers
1935-1967
Flanders, Charles, 1907-1973
3.5 linear ft.
Original daily and Sunday cartoons from the newspaper comic strip The Lone Ranger (1966), correspondence (1935-1967), original drawings and sketches, published material, and original typed continuity script from Fran Striker.
148980
Biographical History
Cartoonist Charles Flanders (1907-1973) began his career as a commercial artist in Buffalo, NY. He moved to New York City in 1928 where he worked for an advertising agency and then as a magazine illustrator before being hired by King Features Syndicate in 1930. For King Features, Flanders worked on several preexisting strips including Tim Tyler's Luck and Bringing Up Father. In the mid-1930s he created comic adaptations of Ivanhoe and Treasure Island for Malcolm Wheeler-Nicholson's New Fun Comics as well as an original strip, Sandra of the Secret Service.
The last work that he did in his own style was a 1935 Sunday strip, Robin Hood. Following that, he and other King Features artists were encouraged to adopt the style of Alex Raymond, whose Flash Gordon, Jungle Jim, and Secret Agent X-9 were very popular. Flanders' emulation was good enough that he eventually was given responsibility for the X-9 strip (1935), followed by King of the Royal Mounted (1936) and The Lone Ranger (1939). Flanders drew the Lone Ranger until 1971, though in his later years he had increasing difficulty and Tom Gill, the artist for the comic book version, often filled in.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Charles Flanders Papers contains the following types of materials:
Cartoons contains 180 original daily cartoons and 26 original Sunday cartoons from the newspaper comic strip The Lone Ranger, from 1963 and 1966. Daily cartoon: traces of graphite, zipatone, brush, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 6 ¾ x 20 in. Sunday cartoon: traces of graphite, brush, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 18 ¾ x 26 ½ in.
Correspondence contains approximately 20 pieces of incoming correspondence (1935-1967, undated) primarily from readers, but also includes letters from cartoonist Jack Kent and comic book artist Joe Sinnott.
Drawings consists of 1 framed original portrait of an Indian chief in full headdress (1966). Untitled: graphite, pen and ink on paper, 12 ¾ x 14 ¾ in.
Published materials consists of books, fanzines, and tear sheets.
Scripts contains a script written by Lone Ranger creator Fran Striker (7 pages), and newspaper clip announcing Striker's death (1962).
Eight original Sketches complete the collection. These are related to The Lone Ranger, including character studies, sketches of trains and sketches of Native American houses, masks, customs and villages (undated). Pencil, crayon, pen and ink on paper, most approx. 8 x 11 in.
Arrangement of the Collection
Daily and Sunday cartoons are arranged separately in chronological order. Other materials are foldered by type. Correspondence is also in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
The Big Book of Fun Comics (National Allied Publications, 1935) has been removed for separate cataloging. This item is noted in the inventory as "Transferred to Rare Books" and can be located via.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Flanders, Charles, 1907-1973.; Striker, Fran, 1903-1962.; King Features Syndicate.; The Lone ranger (comic strip); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Scripts (documents); Sketches.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles Flanders, 1966-1967.
Lone Ranger cartoons from May 1963, gift of John and Susan Harvith, 2017.
Inventory
- The Lone Ranger cartoons
  Click here for detailed inventory.
  - Daily cartoons, 1963 May; 24 (Oversize 3)
    Gift of John and Susan Harvith, 2017.
  - Daily cartoons, 1966 Jan-Jul; 156 (Box 1)
  - Sunday cartoons, 1966 Jan-Jul; 26 (Oversize 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence, 1935-1967; undated; approx. 20 letters (Oversize 2)
- Drawings, 1
  - Untitled [portrait of Indian chief in full headdress], 1966 (Oversize 2)
- Published material
  - The Big Book of Fun Comics, 1935; This book has been transferred to Rare Books for separate cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
  - Ivanhoe [tear sheet], 1935; 1 page (Oversize 2)
  - Men of Mystery no. 4, Aug 1966 (Oversize 2)
- Scripts, 1
  - Typed continuity script by Fran Striker for The Lone Ranger, 24 Sep 1962 - 29 Sep 1962 (Oversize 2)
    hand written note from Flanders: "last continuity from Frank Striker...1962"
  - Newspaper clipping of Fran Striker's death, 1962 (Oversize 1)
- Sketches, 8
  - Figures and scenes for The Lone Ranger (Oversize 2)